{
  "reference_number": "9528",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "I support a 2050 target with the majority of cuts occurring over the next decade."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "I support all greenhouse gases being included in the Zero Carbon Act, consistent with international climate frameworks including the\n Paris Agreement and SDG 13 to “take urgent action to combat climate change and its impacts”."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "I support the ‘firewall’ principle, that New Zealand’s targets must be achieved by actual cuts in our own emissions, and not through\n the purchase of overseas carbon credits or an over-reliance on forests as carbon sinks."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Only in a more ambitious direction (i.e. bring the target forward) under stated provisions such as scientific advances, changes in\n\n international law or unforeseen climate changes (tipping points reached). Any revision should require input from the Climate\n Commission and Parliamentary approval."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I don't know whether five-yearly or six-yearly budgets would be better. Alignment with the electoral cycle may be the better option."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "The Government can introduce policies and strategies to meet the third budget, but should not alter the budget itself unless there is\n good reason. For example, if the emissions cap during the first or second budget was found to be too generous, or if CO2 uptake by\n\n forestry was found to be overestimated, there could be provision in the Act for revising the third budget and setting a tighter cap for\n that period to meet the 2050 target, if so advised by the Climate Change Commission. There would also need to be a clause\n prohibiting budget amendment to a less stringent cap."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Only in exceptional circumstances, such as a major earthquake, if so advised by the Climate Change Commission, and only with\n\nParliamentary approval."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "After each emission budget has been decided, there should be a statutory set timeframe within which the Government must publish\na detailed report on the pathways and policies it intends to implement to meet that budget. The timeframe should be no longer than\nthree months."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "How goods and materials are produced, packaged, transported, and disposed of has implications for emissions reduction. The Zero\n\nCarbon Bill needs to be aligned with the circular economy and legislation relating to biogas production and waste treatment,\nparticularly the Waste Minimisation Act 2008 and the New Zealand Waste Strategy 2010."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We should not think of ourselves as a small player or focus primarily on the local effects of climate change. We can hardly imagine\n\nwhat the world will be like with 1.5°C or 2°C of warming. NZ's net zero goal must reflect our responsibility to devise and implement\nmitigation and adaptation strategies not just for ourselves but for Pasifika nations too."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Government needs to prepare a national climate risk assessment and produce an adaptation programme to address the\nidentified climate risks."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Please see \"Additional notes\" attached."
    }
  ]
}
